Finding Aid for Charles A. Simpson papers, 1910-1932
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles A. Simpson papers 1910-1932.
Simpson, Charles Althen, 1896-1984.
1 linear ft. and 2 outsize folders
Soldier from Grand Rapids, Mich., member of 337th Ambulance Company who served in the Allied intervention in Russia, 1918-1920, the "Polar Bear Expedition." Collection includes diaries and reminiscences of his service in Russia and training at Fort Custer, Michigan; also his diaries of life in Grand Rapids, photographs, motion pictures, and miscellaneous.
87352 Aa 2 Uam
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Elizabeth Plasman and Mrs. Margery Joppe, both of Grand Rapids, Michigan, in 1987 (Donor no.: 7475 ).
The collection is open for research.
Resident of Grand Rapids, Mich., served as private, 337th Ambulance Co.
The collection includes diaries and a reminiscence of his service in Russia, at Obozerskaya and Archangel, and his training at Fort Custer, Mich.; also clippings and miscellanea. The collection also includes views of Fort Custer, Mich., and photos taken in Russia (both U. S. Signal Corps photos and snapshots) of American and allied soldiers, cities and towns, Russian people, battle scenes, and means of transportation; also a motion picture (16 mm original with DVD and streaming file use copies) containing miscellaneous scenes of American troops in Archangel.
Subjects
Simpson, Charles Althen, 1896-1984.; Soviet Union--History--Allied Intervention, 1918-1920.; World War, 1914-1918.; Polar Bear Expedition.; Fort Custer (Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Medical aspects of war.; Military camps.; Military life.; Women--Soviet Union--Work.; Women--War work.; American National Red Cross.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Motion pictures (visual works); Diaries.
- Diaries
  - 1910 and 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Papers
  - Miscellanea,undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memos,1910-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Outsize publications,1918 (Folder 10)
- Visual materials
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photograph album (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photograph album (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oversize photographs (Folder 9 UAm)
  - Motion picture of U.S. troops in Archangel, ca. 1920, 87352-1
    The film includes footage of Northern Russia after Word War I; U.S. soldiers disembarking from ship; dock scenes; unloading baggage at American headquarters; religious procession; Laplanders with reindeer sleighs; U.S. soldiers in formation and marching and soldiers boarding ship.
    - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:04:48
    - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 9)
    - Streaming File: 87352-1, flv